A Guide to the Virginia Secretary of Public Safety Correspondence and Subject Files, 1981-1993 (bulk 1989-1993)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Secretary of Public Safety Correspondence and Subject Files, 1981-1993 (bulk 1989-1993)
The Library of Virginia
34713
11 cubic feet (11 boxes)
Virginia Secretary of Public Safety
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Privacy protected and other protected information is considered confidential and restricted from public access for 75 years. It may be necessary for an archivist to review any unprocessed, modern record collections (those collections less than 75 years old) that may contain confidential information before the records can be used by patrons for research purposes or before any copies of records can be made for patrons. If you are planning to use these records, please contact Archives Reference Services for more details before planning your research trip.
If a request for copies is made for material containing confidential information, it is understood that this information will be redacted from the copies, if it is possible to do so. If redaction is not possible, the records will be withheld. Researchers must also agree that no direct or indirect contact will be made with the individuals to whom any personal or confidential information relates. Improper use and/or re-disclosure of privacy protected information is a breach of confidentiality which could result in the loss of access to the archival collections housed and maintained by The Library of Virginia, and could result in legal penalties (Code of Virginia, 18.2-186.3).
Acquisition Information
Transferred by the Office of the Secretary of Public Safety, Ninth Street Office Building, Richmond, Virginia, July 1994.
Historical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now. Governor Linwood Holton's top priority for the 1972 session of the General Assembly was a proposal for a Governor's Cabinet, reorganizing state agencies into six major departments, each headed by a secretary appointed by the governor. Transportation and public safety was one of these six departments. The office of Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was created on April 8, 1972, by an act passed by the General Assembly. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature established separate secretariats for transportation and for public safety, effective July 1, 1976.
In 1980, Governor John N. Dalton named T. Rodman Layman, an Alcoholic Beverage and Contol Board Commissioner (1970-1980), to succeed H. Selwyn Smith as Secretary of Public Safety. Layman served until the end of Dalton's term in January 1982. Governor-elect Charles S. Robb appointed Franklin E. White, a former criminial justice advisor to President Jimmmy Carter, as Secretary of Public Safety.
On July 1, 1984, the secretariats of transportation and public safety were combined again. As a result of this partial reorganization of state government, Secretary White assumed the duties of the Secretary of Transportation. White resigned in June 1985 and was replaced by Andrew Fogarty, Governor Robb's Secretary of Transportation from 1982-1984, who served until the end of the Robb administration. In December 1985, Governor-elect Gerald L. Baliles, picked Vivian E. Watts, a northern Virginia legislator, as Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. Watts served until the end of Baliles' term in 1990.
On February 22, 1990, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was again divided into separate secretariats. Governor L. Douglas Wilder appointed Colonel Robert L. Suthard, the superintendent of the Virginia State Police, as the Sectretary of Public Safety. Suthard resigned in December 1991 amid allegations that he violated the state's conflict-of-interest law by taking an expenses-paid trip to Japan and a cash gift in April 1991. In March 1992 Wilder appointed O. Randolph Rollins, a Richmond attorney and Deputy Secretary of Public Safety, as Secretary of Public Safety. Rollins served until the end of Governor Wilder's term in January 1994.
Scope and Content
Contains correspondence, subject files and reports created and collected by the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Public Safety. The files relate mostly to the agencies and boards that were under the Secretary's supervision. Files in this collection document the activities of the Department of Alcoholic Beverage Control, Department of Corrections, Department of Criminal Justice Services, Military Advisory Council, and the Virginia State Police. Many files in this accession relate to the cleanup and regulation of Cheatham Annex, a Emergency Fuel Storage Facility that was named an EPA Superfund site. Files pertaining to a variety of smaller agencies, boards, and committees related to public safety are also included.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1981-1993 (bulk 1989-1993)
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1981-1993 (bulk 1989-1993)., Extent: 11 cubic feet. (Box 1-11)
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Alcoholic Beverage Control, Department of (General Correspondence), 1990. (Box 5)
  - Alcoholic Beverage Control, Department of (General Correspondence), 1991. (Box 5)
  - Alcoholic Beverage Control, Department of (General Correspondence), 1992. (Box 5)
  - Alcoholic Beverage Control, Department of (Performance Appraisals), 1987-1988. (Box 5)
  - Alcoholic Beverage Control, Department of (Weedon File), 1990. (Box 1)
  - Camp Pendleton Sale, 1990. (Box 6)
  - Camp Pendleton Sale, 1991. (Box 6)
  - Camp Pendleton Sale (Appraisals), 1990. (Box 6)
  - Camp Pendleton Sale (Rollins, O. Randolph), undated. (Box 6)
  - Camp Pendleton Sale (Studies), 1987-1992. (Box 6)
  - Cheatham Annex, 1991-1992. (Box 3)
  - Cheatham Annex, 1991-1992. (Box 10)
  - Cheatham Annex, 1991-1993. (Box 9)
  - Cheatham Annex (Asbestos), 1991. (Box 1)
  - Cheatham Annex (Capital Outlay, Monthly Reports), 1992-1993. (Box 9)
  - Cheatham Annex (Cleanup), 1990-1991. (Box 1)
  - Cheatham Annex (Cleanup Agreement), 1992. (Box 9)
  - Cheatham Annex (Cleanup Contract), 1991. (Box 9)
  - Cheatham Annex (Compliance Agreement), 1992. (Box 9)
  - Cheatham Annex (Emergency Fuel Storage Facility), 1988. (Box 3)
  - Cheatham Annex (Environmental Remediation), [2 folders], 1991-1992. (Box 3)
  - Cheatham Annex (EPA Agreement), 1991-1992. (Box 1)
  - Cheatham Annex (EPA Civil Penalty Case), 1993. (Box 9)
  - Cheatham Annex (EPA Cleanup Agreement), 1989-1992. (Box 3)
  - Cheatham Annex (EPA/Military Affairs), 1989-1992. (Box 10)
  - Cheatham Annex (Federal Liability), 1991. (Box 10)
  - Cheatham Annex (Hearings), 1990-1991. (Box 9)
  - Cheatham Annex (Operation, Restoration and Regulation), 1991. (Box 10)
  - Cheatham Annex (PCB), 1990-1991. (Box 1)
  - Cheatham Annex (Petroleum Sludge Pits), 1991. (Box 1)
  - Cheatham Annex (Quarterly Status Report), 1992. (Box 9)
  - Cheatham Annex (Regulations), 1990-1991. (Box 10)
  - Cheatham Annex (Reports and Other Documentation), 1981-1991. (Box 11)
  - Cheatham Annex (Request for Assistance), 1991. (Box 9)
  - Cheatham Annex (Rollins, O. Randolph), 1990. (Box 3)
  - Cheatham Annex (Site Cleanup Plan), 1990-1991. (Box 9)
  - Cheatham Annex (Site Safety Plan), 1991. (Box 10)
  - Cheatham Annex (Soil), 1990-1991. (Box 1)
  - Cheatham Annex (University of Virginia Department of Environmental Studies Final Report), [binder], 1990. (Box 9)
  - Cheatham Annex (Update), 1992-1993. (Box 9)
  - Cheatham Annex (Work Plan), 1991. (Box 9)
  - Commonwealth's Attorneys' Services and Training Council (General Correspondence), 1990. (Box 5)
  - Commonwealth's Attorneys' Services and Training Council (General Correspondence), 1991. (Box 5)
  - Commonwealth's Attorneys' Services and Training Council (General Correspondence), 1992. (Box 5)
  - Corrections, Department of (General Correspondence), 1989. (Box 2)
  - Corrections, Department of (General Correspondence), 1990. (Box 5)
  - Corrections, Department of (General Correspondence), 1991. (Box 5)
  - Corrections, Department of (General Correspondence), [2 folders], 1992. (Box 5)
  - Corrections, Department of (General Correspondence), [2 folders], 1993. (Box 5)
  - Corrections, Department of (Governor's Working Papers), 1990-1992. (Box 1)
  - Corrections, Department of (Red Onion), [2 binders], 1989-1993. (Box 1)
  - Corrections, Department of (Stamper, Charles), 1992-1993. (Box 2)
  - Criminal Justice Services, Department of (General Correspondence), 1990. (Box 5)
  - Criminal Justice Services, Department of (General Correspondence), 1991. (Box 5)
  - Criminal Justice Services, Department of (General Correspondence), 1992. (Box 5)
  - Criminal Justice Services, Department of (Performance Appraisals), 1987-1988. (Box 5)
  - Elko Public Safety Complex, [2 folders], 1989-1992. (Box 6)
  - Financial Statements, Monthly, 1989-1992. (Box 8)
  - General Correspondence, 1990 July-August. (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1990 September-November. (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1991 February-March. (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1991 April-May. (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1991 June-July. (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1991 August-September. (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1991 October-November. (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1992 January-February. (Box 7)
  - General Correspondence, 1992 March-April. (Box 7)
  - General Correspondence, 1992 May-June. (Box 7)
  - General Correspondence, 1992 July-August. (Box 7)
  - General Correspondence, 1992 September-October. (Box 7)
  - General Correspondence, 1992 November-December. (Box 7)
  - Governor's Open House, [2 folders] 1990-1991. (Box 6)
  - Governor's Open House, 1992-1993. (Box 8)
  - Governor's Open House (Danville), 1991. (Box 6)
  - Governor's Open House (Eastern Shore), 1991. (Box 6)
  - Governor's Open House (George Mason University), 1990. (Box 6)
  - Governor's Open House (Norfolk), 1990. (Box 6)
  - Governor's Working Papers, 1990-1993. (Box 1)
  - Greekfest, 1989-1990. (Box 2)
  - Laborfest, [3 folders], 1990. (Box 2)
  - Military Advisory Commission, 1986 October. (Box 8)
  - Military Advisory Commission, 1988 May. (Box 8)
  - Military Advisory Commission, 1988 December. (Box 8)
  - Military Advisory Council, 1987-1989. (Box 8)
  - Military Advisory Council, 1989. (Box 8)
  - Military Advisory Council, [2 binders], 1989 May. (Box 8)
  - Military Advisory Council, [binder], 1989 December. (Box 8)
  - Military Advisory Council, [binder], 1990 June. (Box 8)
  - Military Advisory Council, 1992. (Box 8)
  - Military Advisory Council, [binder], 1992. (Box 8)
  - Military Advisory Council (Accomodations), 1990. (Box 8)
  - Military Advisory Council (Meeting Information), 1989. (Box 8)
  - Military Advisory Council (Other Correspondence), 1990. (Box 8)
  - Neighborhood Watch Coalition, 1991-1993. (Box 6)
  - Quarterly Secretarial Review (Office of the Comptroller), 1991. (Box 6)
  - State Police, Department of (General Correspondence), [2 folders], 1990. (Box 1)
  - State Police, Department of (General Correspondence), 1991. (Box 1)
  - State Police, Department of (General Correspondence), [2 folders], 1992. (Box 1)
  - State Police, Department of (Open Recruitment/Lateral Entry Feasibility Study), [binder], 1992. (Box 1)
  - Urban Crime Partnership (City of Richmond), 1990-1991. (Box 6)
  - Violent Event Analysis (City's Homicide Investigation), 1990-1991. (Box 6)